Zubair Abdulla | Curriculum Vitae

5653 S. Blackstone Ave, Unit 2E, Chicago, IL, 60637

☐ 404 933 5850 • ☑ zubair.abdulla@gmail.com

I am a recent PhD graduate in astrophysics from the University of Chicago with a wide-ranging background in lab work, radio astronomy, data reduction, data analysis, and imaging. My goal is to join an ambitious engineering or R&D project with a positive public impact where I can apply my unique experience from a broad research background and continue to learn as part of a collaboration.

Education

University of Chicago

Chicago 2009–2018

PhD/MA in Astronomy and Astrophysics, Advisor: John Carlstrom Thesis: Constraining the Thermal Contents of X-ray Cavities in Galaxy Clusters with Sunyaev Zel'dovich Effect Observations

University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign

Urbana-Champaign

2005–2009

B. Eng in Engineering Physics

Experience

Research Experience.

Research Assistant

University of Chicago, CARMA-SZ collaboration

2010-2018

Instrumentation: Lead a project involving the building of ten 30 GHz heterodyne radio receivers for integration with the **C**ombined **A**rray for **R**esearch in **M**illimeter **A**stronomy, an interferometric radio telescope in Cedar Flat, CA (mmarray.org). In 2012-2013, I spent ~ 3 months on-site installing, aligning, and debugging the instrument in preparation for commissioning observations in 2013.

Data Analysis: My PhD thesis project made use of the data acquired from the newly built 30 GHz CARMA instrument to study the nature of the most powerful outbursts in the universe. I worked with large sets of interferometric data from CARMA, which included noise analysis, calibration, imaging and deconvolution analysis, and modeling.

Other Experience.

Teaching Assistant

University of Chicago

2009-2010

Taught introductory astrophysics and cosmology and instructed lab sessions. I additionally maintained an undergraduate lab that used state-of-the-art technology to measure the Cosmic Microwave Background in following years (2010-2017)

Student Mentor

University of Chicago

2010-2016

Mentored and supervised the work of a visiting graduate student and several undergraduates in both data analysis and lab work: Jonathan Florez (Fisk-Vanderbilt Master's to PhD Bridge Program) and Stephan Reyes, Mike Karfunkle, and Jack Orlowski Scherer (University of Chicago undergraduates). Jonathan, Jack, and Stephen have continued on to graduate programs.

Observer

CARMA 2010–2015

Spent 100+ days on 24/7 observing shifts managing observing queues, troubleshooting telescope array faults, and maintaining telescope health.

Athletic Coach

University of Chicago

2010-2018

Coached the men's ultimate frisbee team at the University of Chicago, teaching sport-specific skills, athleticism, and sportsmanship; Great Lakes Region quarterfinalists (2011, 2013, 2016), Semi-finalist (2014,2018), and Finalist (2017)

Undergraduate Research Assistant

University of Wisconsin

2008

Research Education for Undergraduates (REU) position where I worked on a summer project prototyping a compact variable blackbody temperature load for calibration of a microwave bolometer telescope

Lab Assistant

University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign

2007

Carried out various lab work, soldering and wiring jobs, and cryogenic equipment setup

Technical skills

- o **Programming:** Python, Matlab, TeX; Also basic ability with: C++, IDL
- o Lab work: soldering, cryogenics, basic machining, RF electronics
- o Data Analysis: statistical analysis, modeling, astronomical imaging, fourier analysis, interferometry

Selected Publications

- o Constraints on the Thermal Contents of the X-ray cavities of MS 0735+741 with Sunyaev Zel'dovich Effect Observations. **Abdulla, Zubair** et al. Submitted June 2018 to *The Astrophysical Journal*
- o The XXL Survey: XVII. X-ray and Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Properties of the Redshift 2.0 Galaxy Cluster XLSSC 122. Mantz, Adam B. et al.; **Abdulla, Zubair**. *Astronomy and Astrophysics*, accepted 21 March 2017
- o The Massive and Distant Clusters of WISE Survey: MOO J1142+1527, a $10^{15}M_{\odot}$ Galaxy Cluster at z = 1.19. Gonzalez, Anthony H. et al.; **Abdulla, Zubair**. The Astrophysical Journal Letters, Volume 812, Issue 2, article id. L40, 6 pp. (2015).
- o CARMA Measurements of the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich Effect in RX J1347.5-1145. Plagge, Thomas J. et al.; **Abdulla, Zubair**. *The Astrophysical Journal*, Volume 770, Issue 2, article id. 112, 8 pp. (2013).

References

o Dr. John E. Carlstrom

Kavli Institute for Cosmological Physics and Enrico Fermi Institute
Departments of Astronomy & Astrophysics and Physics (Department Chair)
University of Chicago
5640 S. Ellis Ave
Chicago, IL 60637

☑ jc@kicp.uchicago.edu

▼ 773 882 8211

Additional references available upon request